John E. Hart Papers
John E. Hart Papers
1939-1993
Hart, John E.
.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, writings and memorabilia of American literary scholar John E. Hart.
2458306
Biographical History
Spanning 1939 to 1993, the John E. Hart Papers comprises correspondence, writings and memorabilia of the American literary scholar who taught for 28 years at Albion College. While pursuing advanced degrees (M.A. '40, Ph.D. '54) at Syracuse University, Hart was a student of professor of English Leonard Brown, an innovator in the application of Freudian and Marxian principles to literary critical theory. Reflecting not only Hart's relationships with publishers and authors, the collection also illuminates academic teaching at Syracuse University during the turbulent period just before the Second World War.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence-Subject Files includes incoming letters, manuscripts and printed material. Correspondence includes that of editors (James Laughlin, Charles A. Pearce, John Crowe Ransom, Alan Swallow, Theodore Weiss, Edmund Wilson); novelists (Cole Atwood, Eudora Welty); and poets (Tom Dryce, Carol Ely Harper) associated with with Experiment, one of the many small literary quarterlies which flourished between the post-War period and the mid-sixties. Letters and manuscripts from former fellow Syracuse University student Karl Korstad document the changing academic climate between the 1930s and the McCarthy era.
Five notebooks from his course work with Leonard Brown constitute the bulk of Hart's Writings.
Related Material
Additional material relating to Leonard Brown may be found among the Library's collection of his Papers.
Separated Material
Issues of Experiment are among the Library's cataloged rare book collections.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Radicalism; Hart, John E.; Syracuse University.; American literature -- 20th century.; Literature -- History and criticism.; Clippings (information artifacts); Essays.; Notebooks.; Correspondence.; Authors.; Professors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Aldridge, John W., 1972; 1975 (Box 1)
  - re: Appel, Benjamin, 1985; 1990 (Box 1)
    See also Folsom, Franklin.
  - Appel, Willa, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Atwood, Cole, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Leonard, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Dryce, Tom, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Embler, Weller, 1948; "What Every Engineer Should Know"; offprint, inscribed (Box 1)
  - Experiment, 1949-1950; undated (Box 1)
  - Folsom, Franklin, 1972-1977; 1986; includes photocopies of letters of Ben Appel (Box 1)
  - Harper, Carol Ely, 1949; 1957-1958,; undated (Box 1)
  - Indiana University Writers' Conference, 1948 (Box 1)
  - The Kenyon Review, 1948-1950 (Box 1)
  - Korstad, Karl, 1991-1992
    - "The Attacks on 'Multiculturalism' are Political: Part of the Drive for Continued American Hegemony", manuscript (Box 1)
    - "Black and White Together: Organizing in the South with the Food, Tobacco, Agricultural and Allied Workers Union (FTA-CIO) 1946-1952", manuscript (Box 1)
    - "The Functional Approach", ms. (Box 1)
    - "Syracuse 1937-1942", manuscript, drafts (Box 1)
    - "Syracuse 1942 -- Denou[e]ment: Six Letters from Leonard Brown", manuscript (Box 1)
  - Laughlin, James, 1942-1947; undated (Box 1)
  - The New Yorker, 1942; 1944 (Box 1)
  - Odenwaldschule, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - Pearce, Charles A., 1942 (Box 1)
  - Quarterly Review of Literature, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Ransom, John Crowe, 1948; 1950 (Box 1)
  - Rejection letters, 1942; 1946,; 1948,; undated (Box 1)
  - Shapiro, Karl Jay, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Swallow, Alan, 1946-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Syracuse University, 1938; 1950 (Box 1)
  - University of Cambridge, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - University of Cincinnati, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Weiss, Theodore Russell, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Welty, Eudora, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1944 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Essays
    - "Albert Halper's World of the Thirties," Twentieth Century Literature, Jan 1964; with pen and ink revisions (Box 1)
    - "The Red Badge of Courage as Mythical Symbol," University of Kansas City Review, summer 1953 (Box 1)
  - Notebooks
    - Literary Criticism course with Leonard Brown, 1940; 1949; 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - Main Currents in American Literature course with Leonard Brown, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Main Currents in Modern Literature course with Leonard Brown, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Modern Literature course with Leonard Brown, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Renaissance Studies course with Leonard Brown, 1939-1940; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Summer course with Leonard Brown, Malcolm Cowley, Kenneth Burke", undated (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings, 1993; Albion College retirement honors, with program (Box 2)
  - Clippings, Albion Reporter, 1990 (Box 2)
  - McGraw-Hill Sound Seminars catalog, undated (Box 2)
- Printed material
  - Experiment, spring, summer 1949 (Box 2)
  - Mark Twain Journal, summer 1959; spring 1964,; winter 1972 (Box 2)
  - Tabard, spring 1949; autumn 1949,; undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)